Inventory of the Vladimir L'vovich Burtsev papers
Hoover Institution Archives
Vladimir L'vovich Burtsev papers
1906-1935
66000
Hoover Institution Archives
2 manuscript boxes, 1 envelope (0.9 linear feet)
Memoirs, essays, correspondence, and printed matter, relating to the Menshevik and Social Revolutionary movements before 1917, Evno Azef and other Okhrana agents, and counterrevolutionary movements during the Russian Revolution. Also available on microfilm (2 reels).
Burtsev, Vladimir L'vovich.
Access
Collection is open for research.
The Hoover Institution Archives only allows access to copies of audiovisual items. To listen to sound recordings or to view videos or films during your visit, please contact the Archives at least two working days before your arrival. We will then advise you of the accessibility of the material you wish to see or hear. Please note that not all audiovisual material is immediately accessible.
Acquisition Information
Acquired by the Hoover Institution Archives in 1966.
Accruals
Materials may have been added to the collection since this finding aid was prepared. To determine if this has occurred, find the collection in Stanford University's online catalog at http://searchworks.stanford.edu/. Materials have been added to the collection if the number of boxes listed in the library catalog is larger than the number of boxes listed in this finding aid.
Biographical Note
1862 Born, Russia
1880-1882 Student at the University of St. Petersburg
1882 Expelled from the University of St. Petersburg and exiled to Siberia
1888 Arrived in Zurich, Switzerland and founded the magazine Svobodnaia Rossiia
1897 Began to publish Narodovolets in London
1898 Began to publish Byloe in London
1903 Expelled from France and Switzerland
1909 Exposed Envo Azef as a tsarist provocateur highly placed within the Russian revolutionary movement
1909-1910 Published Obshchee delo
1909-1917 Exposed numerous individuals as tsarist provocateurs
1911-1914 Published Budushchee
1917 March Returned to Russia
1917 October Arrested by the Bolshevik government and escaped from Russia
1917-1922 Published Obshchee delo
1922-1942 Pursued and exposed Soviet agents
1942 Died
Scope and Content of Collection
Memoirs, essays, correspondence, and printed matter, relating to the Menshevik and Social Revolutionary movements before 1917, Evno Azef and other Okhrana agents, and counterrevolutionary movements during the Russian Revolution. Also available on microfilm (2 reels).
Azef, Evno Fishelevich, 1869-1918.; Partiia sotsialistov-revoliutsionerov.; Rossiiskaia sotsial-demokraticheskaia rabochaia partiia.; Russia. Okhrannye Otdeleniia.; Agents provocateurs--Russia.; Revolutionaries--Russia.; Secret service--Russia.; Socialism--Russia.; Soviet Union--History--Revolution, 1917-1921.
- Correspondence, 1912-1936 (Box 1)
  Scope and Contents note
  Correspondence arranged alphabetically by name of correspondent
  - Aleksandr Ivanovich, 1923 (Folder 1: 1)
  - Amfiteatrov, Aleksandr, 1930 (Folder 1: 2)
  - Bernstein, Lev Borisovich, 1919-1927, 1936 (Folder 1: 3)
  - Evgenii Sergeevich, 1923 (Folder 1: 4)
  - Il'in, 1921 (Folder 1: 5)
  - Kirdetsov, 1919 (Folder 1: 6)
  - Kizevetter, Aleksandr A., 1923 (Folder 1: 7)
  - Kolchak, Admiral, 1920 (Folder 1: 8)
  - Konstantin Dmitrievich, 1923 (Folder 1: 9)
  - L.F., 1923 (Folder 1: 10)
  - Pavel Pavlovich, 1923 (Folder 1: 11)
  - Petrunkevich, Ivan Il'ich, 1923 (Folder 1: 12)
  - Rodichev, Fedor Izmailovich, 1923 (Folder 1: 13)
  - Romanovskii, Iurii Dmitrievich, undated (Folder 1: 14)
  - S., 1912 (Folder 1: 15)
  - Semenov, E.P., 1920 (Folder 1: 16)
  - Tyrkova, Ariadna Vladimirovna, 1923 (Folder 1: 17)
  - Vasilii Pavlovich, 1923 (Folder 1: 18)
  - Vassilkovsky, Oleg, 1919 (Folder 1: 19)
  - Vladimir Aleksandrovich, 1923 (Folder 1: 20)
  - Vladislav Karlovich, 1923 (Folder 1: 21)
  - Vrangel', Petr N., 1921 (Folder 1: 22)
  - Miscellaneous (Folder 1: 23)
- Subject file, 1917-1924 (Box 1)
  Articles, reports, memoranda, notes, and printed matter. Arranged alphabetically by subject
  - Amfiteatrov, Aleksandr (Folder 1: 24)
  - Borovikovskii, A., "Ekse Gomo," (Ecce Homo), a poem, 1980 (Folder 1: 25)
    Typewritten carbon copy
  - Clippings (Folder 1: 26)
  - Evalenko, A., provocateur (Folder 1: 27)
  - Evidence provided (in Russian) by V.L. Burtsev, 1917 April 1 (Folder 1: 28)
  - Last will and testament, 1919 (Folder 1: 29)
  - "Pamiatniki Gertsenu i Ogarevu" (Monument to Herzen and Ogarev), typescript, undated (Folder 1: 30)
  - Provocateurs (Folder 1: 31)
  - Radishchev, A.N. (Folder 1: 32)
  - Russia--History--Revolution, 1917-1921 (Folder 1: 33)
  - Sazonov, Sergei, letters, undated (Folder 1: 34)
  - Société de la Jeunesse Slave (Folder 1: 35)
  - "Strashnye dni v Tomske--Iz dnevnika ochevidtsa,", undated (Folder 1: 36)
  - "Tri dnia--Iz dnevnika proshedshago,", undated (Folder 1: 37)
- Speeches and writings, 1908-1934 (Box 1-2)
  Drafts and printed copies of speeches and writings. Arranged alphabetically by title or subject
  - "Agent Leit," typescript, undated (Folder 1: 38)
  - "Agent Lerua," typescript, undated (Folder 1: 39)
  - "Bor'ba so mnoi reaktsionerov Gen. Klimovicha i Shtiumera," typewritten carbon copy, 1916 (Folder 1: 40)
  - "Delo chlena Gos. Dumy Pianykh," typescript, 1916 (Folder 1: 41)
  - "Delo Rappoporta," typescript, undated (Folder 1: 42)
  - "Delo Stanislava Bzhozovskago i Borovskoi," typescript, undated (Folder 1: 43)
  - "Itogi bylova i zadachi budushchago--Iz moikh vospominanii. Glava I. Gvozd' kotorym byl raspiat Khristos," typewritten carbon copy, undated (Folder 1: 44)
    Pages missing
  - "K druz'iam Budushchago," printed copy, undated (Folder 1: 45)
  - "K tem, kto liubit svobodu," holograph and typewritten copy, 1913 (Folder 1: 46)
  - "Moi prizyv k otkrytoi bor'be," typewritten carbon copy, undated (Folder 1: 47)
  - "Moia bor'ba s provokatorami," typescript, undated (Folder 1: 48)
  - "Moia perepiska i moi svidaniia s liud'mi potustoroniago mira," typescript with annotations, undated (Folder 1: 49)
  - "Moia perepiska iz zagranitsy s pravitel'stvennymi i ofitsial'nymi litsami," typescript, undated (Folder 1: 50)
  - "Moia perepiska s Zubatovym," typescript with annotations, 1908 (Folder 1: 51)
  - "Moi otnosheniia s Okhrannikami," typewritten carbon copy, undated (Folder 1: 52)
  - "Moi vospominaniia," table of contents, undated (Folder 1: 53)
  - "Nachalo Izdaniia Obshchago dela," typescript, undated (Folder 1: 54)
  - "Neobkhodimost' imet' obshchenational'nyi organ," typescript, 1909 (Folder 1: 55)
  - "Osnovanie Budushchago," typewritten carbon copy, undated (Folder 1: 56)
  - "Otnoshenie emigrantov k Men'shchikovu," typewritten carbon copy, undated (Folder 1: 57)
  - "Peregovory Men'shchikova s emigrantami," typewritten carbon copy, undated (Folder 1: 58)
  - "Priezd zagranitsu Men'shchikova," typewritten carbon copy, undated (Folder 1: 59)
  - "Po povodu pis'ma g. Ivanova," holograph, undated (Folder 1: 60)
  - Pushkin, Aleksandr S., articles about, typewritten carbon copies, undated (Folder 1: 61)
  - Provocateurs, untitled collection of articles regarding V.L. Burtsev's activities in exposing them, typescript, undated (Folder 1: 62)
  - "Provokatorsha Putiata," typewritten carbon copy, undated (Folder 2: 1)
  - "Russkii Revoliutsioner strelial v nachal'nika okhrannogo otdeleniia," typewritten carbon copy, undated (Folder 2: 2)
  - "Semenov," typescript, undated (Folder 2: 3)
  - Shakespeare, William, an untitled work (in Russian) about, typescript, 1924 (Folder 2: 4)
  - "Shakhov," typescript, undated (Folder 2: 5)
  - "Tainoe svidanie s Azefom," typewritten carbon copy, undated (Folder 2: 6)
  - "Tovarishcham Sotsial'demokratu," typewritten carbon copy, 1909 (Folder 2: 7)
  - "Tri osnovnyie zadachi," typescript, undated (Folder 2: 8)
  - "Vera v budushchee," typescript, undated (Folder 2: 9)
  - "V.L. Burtsev o svidanii s Azefom," Russkoe slovo, no. 183, 1912 (Folder 2: 10)
  - "Vospominaniia o Portsmutskom Mire," galley proofs, undated (Folder 2: 11)
  - "Vospominaniia ob Azeve," typewritten carbon copy, 1934 (Folder 2: 12)
  - "Vystuplenie Men'shikova protiv menia pod pokrovitel'stvom nekotorykh emigrantov," typewritten carbon copy, undated (Folder 2: 13)
  - Miscellaneous drafts and notes (Folder 2: 14)
  - Untitled writings (Folder 2: 15)
  - Miscellany (Folder 2: 16)
- Photographs
  - 9 photographs depicting Vladimir L. Burtsev. Includes one print of a bust of Burtsev with the sculptress, taken circa 1909-1910 (Envelope A)